<section id="advanced-discussions-proof-of-nonexistence">
 <title>Proof of Non-Existence (NSEC and NSEC3) </title>
 <para>How do you prove that something does not exist? This zen-like question
 is an interesting one, and in this section we will provide an overview of how
 DNSSEC solves the problem.</para>

 <para>Why is it even important to have authenticated denial of existence?
 Couldn't we just send back a "hey, what you asked for does not exist", and
 somehow generate a digital signature to go with it, proving it really is from
 the correct authoritative source? Well, the technical challenge of signing
 nothing aside, this solution has flaws, one of which is it gives an attacker a
 way to create the appearance of denial of service by replaying this message on
 the network.</para>

 <para>We are going to use a little story, and tell it three different times to
 illustrate how proof of nonexistence works. In our story, we run a small
 company with three employees: Alice, Edward, and Susan. We list their names in
 a phone directory, and we hired a nameless intern to answer our phone
 calls.</para>

 <para>If we followed the approach of giving back the same answer no matter
 what was asked, when people called and asked for "Bob", our intern would
 simply answer: "Sorry, that person doesn't work here, and to prove that I am
 not lying, here's the signature: 'deaf coffee beef'". Now this is a legitimate
 answer, but since the signature doesn't change,  an attacker could record this
 message, and when the next person called in asking for Susan, she will hear
 the exact same message: "Sorry, that person doesn't work here, and to prove
 that I am not lying, here's the signature: 'deaf coffee beef'". And this
 answer is verifiable, since the magic signature ("deaf coffee beef" ) can be
 validated <footnote><para>Actually it cannot be verified, read <xref
 linkend="how-are-answers-verified" /> to review why this would not
 work.</para></footnote>. Now the attacker has successfully fooled the caller
 into thinking that Susan doesn't work at our company, and might even be able
 to convince all callers that no one works at this company (no names
 exist).</para>

 <para>To solve this problem, two different solutions were created, we will
 look at the first one, NSEC, next.</para>

 
 <!-- === NSEC === -->
 <section id="advanced-discussions-nsec">
  <title>NSEC</title>
  <para>The NSEC record is used to prove that something really does not exist,
  by providing the name before it, and the name after it. Using our tiny
  company example, this would be analogous to someone calling for Bob over the
  phone, and our nameless intern answered the phone with: "I'm sorry, that
  person doesn't work here. The name before that is Alice, and the name after
  that is Edward". Let's say someone called in again for a non-existent person,
  Oliver, the answer would be: "I'm sorry, that person doesn't work here. The
  name before that is Edward, and the name after that is Susan". Another caller
  asked for Todd, and the answer would be: "I'm sorry, that person doesn't work
  here. The name before that is Susan, and the name after that is
  Alice".</para>

  <para>So we end up with three NSEC records:
   <screen>alice.example.com.  300	IN	NSEC	edward.example.com. A RRSIG NSEC
edward.example.com. 300	IN	NSEC	susan.example.com.  A RRSIG NSEC
susan.example.com.  300	IN	NSEC	alice.example.com.  A RRSIG NSEC</screen>

  </para>

  <para>What if the attacker tried to use the same replay method described
  earlier? If someone called for Edward, none of the three answers would fit.
  If attacker played message #1, "I'm sorry, that person doesn't work here. The
  name before it is Alice, and the name after it is Edward", it is obviously
  false, since "Edward" is in the response; same for #2, Edward and Susan. As
  for #3, Edward does not fall in range after Susan or before Alice, and the
  caller can logically deduct that it was an incorrect answer.</para>

  <para>In BIND inline signing, your zone data will be automatically sorted on
  the fly before generating NSEC records, much like how a phone directory is
  sorted.</para>

  <para>Unfortunately, the NSEC solution has a few drawbacks, one of which is
  trivial "zone walking". A curious person can keep calling back, and our
  nameless, gullible intern will keep divulging information about our
  employees. Imagine if the caller first asked: "Is Bob there?" and received
  back the names Alice and Edward. The caller can then call back again: "Is
  Edward-a there?", and will get back Edward and Susan. Repeat the process
  enough times, the caller will eventually learn every name in our company
  phone directory. For many of you, this may not be a problem, since the very
  idea of DNS is similar to a public phone book: if you don't want a name to be
  known publicly, don't put it in DNS!</para>

  <para>The second drawback of NSEC is a actually increased operational
  overhead: no opt-out mechanism for insecure child zones, this generally is a
  problem for parent zone operators dealing with a lot of insecure child zones,
  such as <code>.com</code>. To learn more about opt-out, please see <xref
  linkend="advanced-discussions-nsec3-optout" />.</para> </section>


 <!-- === NSEC3 === -->
 <section id="advanced-discussions-nsec3">
  <title>NSEC3</title>
  <para>NSEC3 adds two additional features that NSEC does not have:
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>No easy zone enumeration.</simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>Provides a mechanism for child zone to opt out.</simpara>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
  </para>

  <para>Recall, in <xref linkend="advanced-discussions-nsec" />, we provided a
  range of names to prove that something really does not exist. But as it turns
  out, even disclosing these ranges of names becomes a problem: this made it
  very easy for the curious minded to look at your entire zone. Not only that,
  unlike a zone transfer, this "zone walking" is more resource intensive. So
  how do we disclose something, without actually disclosing it?</para>

  <para>The answer is actually quite simple, hashing functions, or one-way
  hashes. Without going into many details, think of it like a magical meat
  grinder. A juicy piece of ribeye steak goes in one end, and out comes a
  predictable shape and size of ground meat (hash) with a somewhat unique
  pattern. No matter how hard you try, you cannot turn the ground meat back
  into the juicy ribeye steak, that's what we call a one-way hash.</para>

  <para>NSEC3 basically runs the names through a one-way hash, before giving it
  out, so the recipients can verify the non-existence, without any knowledge of
  the actual names.</para>

  <para>So let's tell our little phone receptionist story for the third time,
  this time with NSEC3. This time, our intern is not given a list of actual
  names, he is given a list of "hashed" names. So instead of Alice, Edward, and
  Susan, the list he is given reads like this (hashes shortened for easier
  reading):
   <screen>FSK5....  (produced from Edward)
JKMA.... (produced from Susan)
NTQ0.... (produced from Alice)</screen></para>

  <para>Then, the phone rings, someone's asking for Bob again. Our intern takes
  the name Bob through a hash function, and the result is L8J2..., so he tells
  them on the phone: "I'm sorry, that person doesn't work here. The name before
  that is JKMA..., and the name after that is NTQ0...". There, we proved Bob
  doesn't exist, without giving away any names! To put that into proper NSEC3
  resource records, they would look like this (again, hashes shortened for
  display):
   <screen>FSK5....example.com. 300 IN NSEC3 1 0 10 1234567890ABCDEF  JKMA... A RRSIG
JKMA....example.com. 300 IN NSEC3 1 0 10 1234567890ABCDEF  NTQ0... A RRSIG
NTQ0....example.com. 300 IN NSEC3 1 0 10 1234567890ABCDEF  FSK5... A RRSIG</screen>

  </para>

  <para>Some of you who paid attention earlier may recognize the numbers here
  1, 0, 10, and 1234567890ABCDEF from <xref linkend="signing-using-nsec3" />,
  then you will remember that these four parameters represent algorithm,
  opt-out, iterations, and salt, respectively. We will discuss more about
  opt-out in <xref linkend="advanced-discussions-nsec3-optout" /> and salt in
  <xref linkend="advanced-discussions-nsec3-salt" />.</para>


<note><title>Hashes and Privacy</title> Just because we employed one-way hash
functions does not mean there's no way for a determined individual to figure
out what your zone data is. Someone could still gather all of your NSEC3
records and hashed names, and perform an offline brute-force attack by trying
all possible combinations to figure out what the original name is. This would
be like if someone really wanted to know how you got the ground meat, he could
buy all cuts of meat and ground it up at home, and compare the output with the
meat you gave him. It is expensive and time consuming (especially with real
meat), but like everything else in cryptography, if someone has enough
resources and time, nothing is truly private forever. If you are concerned
about someone performing this type of attack on your zone data, see about adding
salt as described in <xref linkend="advanced-discussions-nsec3-salt"/>.</note>

 <!-- === NSEC3PARAM === -->
 <section id="advanced-discussions-nsec3param">
  <title>NSEC3PARAM</title>
  <para>In <xref linkend="signing-using-nsec3" />, our example used four
  parameters: 1, 0, 10, and 1234567890ABCDEF, in the order they appeared. It
  looked like this:
   <screen># <userinput>rndc signing -nsec3param 1 0 10 1234567890abcdef example.com</userinput></screen>
  
  </para>

  <para>1 represents the algorithm, 0 represents the opt-out flag, 10
  represents the number of iterations, and 1234567890abcedf is the salt. Let's
  look at how each one can be configured:
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <simpara><emphasis>Algorithm</emphasis>: Not much of a choice here, the
     only defined value currently is 1 for SHA-1.</simpara></listitem>

    <listitem>
     <simpara><emphasis>Opt-out</emphasis>: Set this to 1 if you want to do
     NSEC3 opt-out, which we will discuss in <xref
     linkend="advanced-discussions-nsec3-optout" />.</simpara></listitem>

    <listitem>
     <simpara><emphasis>Iterations</emphasis>: iterations defines the number of
     additional times to apply the algorithm when generating an NSEC3 hash.
     More iterations yields more secure results, but consumes more resources
     for both authoritative server sand validating resolvers. In the regard, we
     have similar considerations as we've seen in <xref linkend="key-sizes"
     /> of security versus resources.</simpara></listitem>

    <listitem>
     <simpara><emphasis>Salt</emphasis>: The salt is a string of data expressed
     in hexadecimal, or a hyphen (‘-’) if no salt is to be used. We will learn
     more about salt in <xref linkend="advanced-discussions-nsec3-salt"
     />.</simpara></listitem>

   </itemizedlist></para>

   <para>For example, to create an NSEC3 chain using the SHA-1 hash algorithm,
   no opt-out flag, 10 iterations, and a salt value of "FFFF", use: 
    <screen># <userinput>rndc signing -nsec3param 1 0 10 FFFF example.com</userinput></screen>
   
   </para>

   <para>To set the opt-out flag, 15 iterations, and no salt, use: 
    <screen># <userinput>rndc signing -nsec3param 1 1 15 - example.com</userinput></screen>

   </para>
 </section>

 <!-- === NSEC3 Opt-out === -->
 <section id="advanced-discussions-nsec3-optout">
  <title>NSEC3 Opt-Out</title>
  <para>One of the advantages of NSEC3 over NSEC is the ability for parent
  zones to publish less information about insecure child (delegated) zones,
  thus reducing overhead on the parent zone's name servers.</para>

  <para>This may not seem like a lot, but imagine in if you are the operator of
  busy top level domains such as <code>.com</code> or <code>.net</code>, with
  millions and millions of insecure delegated domain names, it quickly adds up.
  As of late 2014, less than 0.1% of all <code>.com</code> zones are signed.
  Basically, without opt-out, if you have 50,000 delegations, only 5 of which
  are secure, you still have to sign all 50,000 delegated names; with NSEC3
  opt-out, you will only sign a set of delegated names if there is at least one
  DS record present, indicating that the delegated name is secure. So with
  opt-out, instead of signing 50,000 sets of delegations indiscriminately, you
  will only sign 5 sets of delegations.</para>

  <para>But for most DNS administrators who do not manage a large number of
  delegations, the decision whether or not to use NSEC3 opt-out is probably not
  relevant.</para>

  <para>To learn more about how to configure NSEC3 opt-out, please see <xref
  linkend="recipes-nsec3-optout" />.</para>
 </section>

 <!-- === NSEC3 Salt === -->
 <section id="advanced-discussions-nsec3-salt">
  <title>NSEC3 Salt</title>
  <para>As described in <xref linkend="advanced-discussions-nsec3" />, while
  NSEC3 doesn't put your zone data in plain public display, it is still not
  difficult for an attacker to collect all the hashed names, and perform an
  offline attack. All that is required is running through all the combinations
  to construct a database of plaintext names to hashed names, also known as a
  "rainbow table".</para>

  <para>There is one more features NSEC3 gives us to provide additional
  protection: salt. Basically, salt gives us the ability introduce further
  randomness into the hashed results. Whenever the salt is changed, any
  pre-computed rainbow table is rendered useless, and a new rainbow table must
  be re-computed. If the salt is changed from time to time, it becomes
  difficult to construct a useful rainbow table, thus difficult to walk the DNS
  zone data programmatically. How often you want to change your NSEC3 salt is
  up to you.</para>

  <para>To learn more about what steps to take to change NSEC3, please see
  <xref linkend="recipes-nsec3-salt" />.</para> </section>
</section>

 <!-- === NSEC or NSEC3 === -->
 <section id="advanced-discussions-nsec-or-nsec3">
  <title>NSEC or NSEC3?</title>
  <para>So which one should you choose? NSEC or NSEC3? There is not really a
  single right answer here that fits everyone. It all comes down to your needs
  or requirements.</para>

  <para>If you prefer not to make your zone easily enumerable, implementing
  NSEC3 paired with a new salt periodically will provide a certain level of
  privacy protection. However, someone could still randomly guess the names in
  your zone (such as 'ftp' or 'www'), as in the traditional insecure
  DNS.</para>

  <para>If you have many many delegations, and have a need for opt-out to save
  resources, NSEC3 is for you.</para>

  <para>Other than that, using NSEC is typically a good choice for most zone
  administrators, as it relieves the authoritative servers from additional
  cryptographic operations NSEC3 requires, and NSEC is comparatively easier to
  troubleshoot than NSEC3.</para> </section>
</section>
