<section id="other-topics">
 <title>Other Topics</title>

 <!-- === DNSSEC and Dynamic Updates === -->
 <section id="dnssec-and-dynamic-updates">
  <title>DNSSEC and Dynamic Updates</title>
  <para>Dynamic DNS (DDNS) actually is independent of DNSSEC. DDNS provides a
  mechanism other than editing the zone file or zone database, to edit DNS
  data. Most clients and DNS servers have the capability to handle dynamic
  updates, and DDNS can also be integrated as part of your DHCP
  environment.</para>

  <para>When you have both DNSSEC and dynamic updates in your environment,
  updating zone data works the same way as with traditional (insecure) DNS: you
  can use <command>rndc freeze</command> before editing the zone file, and
  <command>rndc thaw</command> when you have finished editing, or you could use
  the command <command>nsupdate</command> to add, edit, or remove records like
  this:
   <screen>$ <userinput>nsupdate</userinput>
> server 192.168.1.13
> update add xyz.example.com. 300 IN A 1.1.1.1
> send
> quit</screen></para>

  <para>The examples provided in this guide will make <command>named</command>
  automatically re-sign the zone whenever its content has changed. If you
  decide to sign your own zone file manually, you will need to remember to
  executed the <command>dnssec-signzone</command> whenever your zone file has
  been updated.</para>

  <para>As far as system resources and performance is concerned, be mindful
  that when you have a DNSSEC zone that changes frequently, every time the zone
  changes, your system is executing a series of cryptographic operations to
  (re)generate signatures and NSEC or NSEC3 records.</para>
 </section>

 <!-- === DNSSEC and Inline Signing === -->
 <section id="dnssec-and-inline-signing">
  <title>DNSSEC and Inline Signing</title>
 </section>

 <!-- === DNSSEC Look-aside Validation === -->
 <section id="dlv">
  <title>DNSSEC Look-aside Validation (DLV)</title>
 </section>

 <!-- === DNSSEC on Private Networks === -->
 <section id="dnssec-on-private-networks">
  <title>DNSSEC on Private Networks</title>
 </section>

 <!-- === Intro to DANE === -->
 <section id="introduction-to-dane">
  <title>Introduction to DANE</title>
 </section>
</section>
