<section id="advanced-discussions-key-storage">
 <title>Key Storage</title>

 <!-- === Private Key Storage === -->
 <section id="private-key-storage">
  <title>Private Key Storage</title>

  <para>Ideally, private keys should be stored offline, in devices such as a smart card. Operationally, however, this creates certain challenges, since we need the private key to create RRSIG resource records, and it would be a hassle to bring the private key out of storage every time the zone file changes or when signatures expire.</para>

  <para>One way around this is to have two sets of keys, a ZSK and KSK. ZSK private key is used to sign zone data, and can be kept online for ease of use; KSK private key is used to sign just the DNSKEY (the ZSK), it is used less frequently, and can be stored in a much more secure and restricted fashion.</para>

  <para>For example, a KSK private key stored on a USB flash drive that is kept in a fireproof safe, only brought online once a month to sign a new pair of ZSK, combined with a ZSK private key stored on the network file-system available for routine use, maybe be a good a good balance between operational flexibility and security.</para>

  <para>And don't forget to change these keys regularly, as described in <xref linkend="key-rollovers" />.</para>
 </section>

 <!-- === HSMs === -->
 <section id="hardware-security-modules">
  <title>Hardware Security Modules (HSM)</title>
  <para>A Hardware Security Module (HSM) comes in different shapes and sizes, but as the name indicates, it's a physical device or devices, usually with some or all of the following features:
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><simpara>Tamper-resistant key storage</simpara></listitem>
    <listitem><simpara>Strong random number generation</simpara></listitem>
    <listitem><simpara>Hardware for faster cryptographic operations</simpara></listitem>
   </itemizedlist></para>

  <para>Most organizations do not incorporate HSMs into their security practices due to cost and the added operational complexity.</para>

  <para>BIND supports PKCS #11 (Public Key Cryptography Standard #11) for communication with HSMs and other cryptographic support devices. For more information on how to configure BIND to work with HSMs, please refer to the <ulink url="http://www.isc.org/downloads/bind/doc/">BIND 9 Administrator Reference Manual</ulink>.</para>
 </section>
</section>
