<section id="disadvantages-of-dnssec">
 <title>Disadvantages of DNSSEC</title>
 <para>DNSSEC, like many things in this world, is not perfect and without its
 own problems. Below are a few challenges and disadvantages that DNSSEC faces.

  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <simpara><emphasis>Increased, well, everything</emphasis>: With DNSSEC,
    signed zones are larger, thus taking up more disk space; for DNSSEC-aware
    servers, the additional cryptographic computation usually results in
    increased system load; and the network packets are bigger, possibly putting
    more strains on the network infrastructure.</simpara>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <simpara><emphasis>Different security considerations</emphasis>: DNSSEC
    addresses many security concerns, most notably cache poisoning. But at the
    same time, it may introduce a set of different security considerations,
    such as amplification attack and zone enumeration through NSEC. These new
    concerns are still being identified and addressed by the Internet
    community.</simpara>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <simpara><emphasis>More complexity</emphasis>: If you have read this far,
    you probably already concluded this yourself. With additional resource
    records, keys, signatures, rotations, DNSSEC adds a lot more moving pieces
    on top of the existing DNS machine. The job of the DNS administrator
    changes, as DNS becomes the new secure repository of everything from spam
    avoidance to encryption keys, and the amount of work involved to
    troubleshoot a DNS-related issue becomes more challenging.</simpara>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <simpara><emphasis>Increased fragility</emphasis>: The increased complexity
    means more opportunities for things to go wrong. In the absence of DNSSEC,
    DNS was essentially "add something to the zone and forget".  With DNSSEC,
    each new component - re-signing, key rollover, interaction with parent
    zone, key management - adds more scope for error. It is entirely possible
    that the failure to validate a name is down to errors on the part of one or
    more zone operators rather than the result of a deliberate attack on the
    DNS.</simpara>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <simpara><emphasis>New maintenance tasks</emphasis>: Even if your new
    secure DNS infrastructure runs without any hiccups or security breaches, it
    still requires regular attention, from re-signing to key rollovers. While
    most of these can be automated, some of the tasks, such as KSK rollover,
    remain manual for the time being. </simpara>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <simpara><emphasis>Not enough people are using it today</emphasis>: while
    it's estimated as of late 2016, that roughly 28% of the global Internet DNS
    traffic is validating
    <footnote><para>based on APNIC statistics at
    <ulink url="http://stats.labs.apnic.net/dnssec/XA" />
    </para></footnote>
    , that doesn't mean that many of the DNS zones are
    actually signed. What this means is, if you signed your company's zone
    today, only less than 30% of the Internet users are taking advantage of
    this extra security. It gets worse, with less than 1% of the .com domains
    signed, if you enabled DNSSEC validation today, it's not likely to buy you
    or your users a whole lot more protection, until these popular domains
    names decide to sign their zones.</simpara>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </para>

 <para>The last point may have more impact than you realize. Consider
 this: HTTP and HTTPS traffic make up majority of the web. While you may
 have secured your DNS infrastructure through DNSSEC, if your web hosting
 is outsourced to a third party that does not yet support DNSSEC in their
 own domain, or if your web page loads contents and components from
 insecure domains, the end users may experience validation problems when
 trying to access your web page. For example, although I may have signed
 the zone <code>isc.org</code>, but my web address
 <code>www.isc.org</code> is actually a CNAME to
 <code>96d719dc5612761de516fc.random-cloud-provider.com</code>. As long
 as <code>random-cloud-provider.com</code> remains an insecure DNS zone,
 users cannot fully validate everything when they visit my web page and
 could be redirected elsewhere by a cache poisoning attack.</para>

</section>
