<section id="signing-maintenance-tasks">
 <title>Maintenance Tasks</title>



 <para>Zone data is signed, parent zone has published your DS records, at this point your zone is officially secure. When other validating resolvers lookup information in your zone, they are able to follow the 12-step process as described in <xref linkend="how-does-dnssec-change-dns-lookup-revisited" /> and verify the authenticity and integrity of the answers.</para>

 <para>There is not that much left for you to do, as the DNS administrator, at an ongoing basis. Whenever you update your zone, BIND will automatically resign your zone with new RRSIG and NSEC or NSEC3 records, and even increment the serial number for you.</para>

 <para>That leaves DNSKEY records. Just like passwords and underwear, keys need to be changed periodically. If you followed the examples in this guide with inline signing and automatic key management, you need to do the following two things regularly:
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>Generate new ZSK pair every month, wait some period of time, and delete old information from zone.</simpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>Generate new KSK pair every year, upload to parent zone, wait some period of time, and delete old information from zone.</simpara>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist></para>

 <para>We will talk more about the details of key rollover and timing in <xref linkend="key-rollovers" />.</para>

 <!-- Monthly Tasks -->
 <section id="monthly-tasks">
  <title>Monthly Tasks</title>
  <para>  Every month, you should generate a new ZSK pair for each DNSSEC zone. No service reload or restart is required, if you followed the examples in this guide. New zone data will be generated automatically.
   <screen># <userinput>cd /etc/bind/keys/example.com</userinput>
# <userinput>dnssec-keygen -a RSASHA256 -b 1024 -3 example.com</userinput>
Generating key pair...++++++ .............++++++ 
Kexample.com.+008+12345</screen></para>

  <para>You should wait a period of time before removing the old signatures and keys from your zone, and this time depends on the length of your TTL and RRSIG validity time. If you used all default values from BIND, wait at least 30 days before deleting these from your zone. See <xref linkend="how-long-before-deleting-old-data" /> to learn more.</para>

  <para>So if you started using the first set (let's call it set A) of ZSK in January, you should generate a new set (set B) in February, and in March, generate set C, and remove information from set A.</para>

  <note>Need help with this section</note>
 </section>

 <!-- Annual Tasks -->
 <section id="annual-tasks">
  <title>Annual Tasks</title>
  <para>Every year, you should generate a new KSK pair for each DNSSEC zone:
   <screen># <userinput>cd /etc/bind/keys/example.com</userinput>
# <userinput>dnssec-keygen -a RSASHA256 -b 4096 -3 -f KSK example.com</userinput>
Generating key pair........................+++ ..................................+++ 
Kexample.com.+008+54321</screen></para>

  <para>And follow the steps in <xref linkend="working-with-parent-zone" /> to generate and upload the information to your parent zone.</para>

  <note>Need help with this section</note>
 </section>
</section>
