<!-- === Software Requirement === -->
<section id="software-requirement">
 <title>Software Requirement</title>

 <!-- =====  BIND Version ====== -->
 <section id="bind-version">
  <title>BIND Version</title>
  <para>The configuration examples given in this document require BIND
  version 9.16.0 or newer (although many should work
  with all versions of BIND later than 9.9). To check the version of
  <command>named</command> you have installed, use the <option>-v</option>
  switch as shown below:

   <screen># <userinput>named -v</userinput>
BIND 9.16.0 (Stable Release) &lt;id:6270e602ea&gt;</screen>
  </para>
 </section>


 <!-- ====== Check BIND if DNSSEC-capable ====== --> 
 <section id="dnssec-support-in-bind">
  <title>DNSSEC Support in BIND</title>
  <para>All versions of BIND 9 since BIND 9.7 can support DNSSEC as currently
  deployed in the global DNS. The BIND software you are
  running most likely already supports DNSSEC as shipped. Run the command
  <command>named -V</command> to see what flags it was built with. If it was
  built with OpenSSL (<option>--with-openssl</option>), then it supports
  DNSSEC. Below is an example screenshot of running <command>named
  -V</command>:

  <screen>$ <userinput>named -V</userinput>
BIND 9.16.0 (Stable Release) &lt;id:6270e602ea&gt;
running on Linux x86_64 4.9.0-9-amd64 #1 SMP Debian 4.9.168-1+deb9u4 (2019-07-19)
built by make with defaults
compiled by GCC 6.3.0 20170516
compiled with OpenSSL version: OpenSSL 1.1.0l  10 Sep 2019
linked to OpenSSL version: OpenSSL 1.1.0l  10 Sep 2019
compiled with libxml2 version: 2.9.4
linked to libxml2 version: 20904
compiled with json-c version: 0.12.1
linked to json-c version: 0.12.1
compiled with zlib version: 1.2.8
linked to zlib version: 1.2.8
threads support is enabled

default paths:
  named configuration:  /usr/local/etc/named.conf
  rndc configuration:   /usr/local/etc/rndc.conf
  DNSSEC root key:      /usr/local/etc/bind.keys
  nsupdate session key: /usr/local/var/run/named/session.key
  named PID file:       /usr/local/var/run/named/named.pid
  named lock file:      /usr/local/var/run/named/named.lock</screen>
  </para>

  <para>If the BIND 9 software you have does not support DNSSEC, you should
  upgrade it. (It has not been possible to build BIND without DNSSEC support since BIND
  9.13, released in 2018.) As well as missing out on DNSSEC support, you are
  also missing out on a number of security fixes made to the software in recent
  years.</para>

 </section>


 <!-- ====== System Entropy ====== --> 
 <section id="system-entropy">
  <title>System Entropy</title>
  <para>If you plan on deploying DNSSEC to your authoritative server, you will
  need to generate cryptographic keys (<xref
  linkend="signing-generate-keys-explained"/>). The amount of time it takes to
  generate the keys depends on the source of randomness, or entropy, on your
  systems. On some systems (especially virtual machines) with insufficient
  entropy, it may take much longer than one cares to wait to generate
  keys.</para>

  <para>There are software packages, such as <command>haveged</command> for
  Linux, that provides additional entropy for your system. Once installed, they
  will significantly reduce the time needed to generate keys.</para>

  <para>The more entropy there is, the better pseudo-random numbers you get,
  and stronger keys are generated. If you want or need high quality random
  numbers, take a look at <xref linkend="hardware-security-modules" /> for some
  of the hardware-based solutions.</para>

 </section>
</section>
