<!-- === Hardware Requirement === -->
<section id="hardware-requirement">
 <title>Hardware Requirement</title>

 <section id="recursive-server-hardware">
  <title>Recursive Server Hardware</title>
  <para>Enabling DNSSEC validation on a recursive server makes it a validating
  resolver. The job of a validating resolver is to fetch additional information
  that can be used to computationally verify the answer set. Below are the
  areas that should be considered for possible hardware enhancement for a
  validating resolver:

  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <simpara><emphasis>CPU</emphasis>: a validating resolver executes
    cryptographic functions on many of the answers returned, this usually leads
    to increased CPU usage, unless your recursive server has built-in hardware
    to perform cryptographic computations.</simpara>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <simpara><emphasis>System memory</emphasis>: DNSSEC leads to larger answer
    sets, and will occupy more memory space.</simpara>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <simpara><emphasis>Network interfaces</emphasis>: although DNSSEC does
    increase the amount of DNS traffic overall, it is unlikely that you need to
    upgrade your network interface card (NIC) on the name server, unless you
    have some truly out-dated hardware.</simpara>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist></para>

  <para>One of the factors to consider is the destinations of your current DNS
  traffic. If your current users spend a lot of time visiting <code>.gov</code>
  web sites, then you should expect a bigger jump in all of the above
  categories when validation is enabled, because <code>.gov</code> is more than
  80% signed. This means, more than 80% of the time, your validating resolver
  will be doing what is described in <xref
  linkend="how-does-dnssec-change-dns-lookup" />. However, if your users only
  care about resources in the <code>.com</code> domain, which as of this
  writing, is less than 0.1% signed, then your recursive name server is
  unlikely to experience significant load increase after enabling DNSSEC
  validation.</para>
 </section>

 <section id="authoritative-server-hardware">
  <title>Authoritative Server Hardware</title>
  <para>On the authoritative server side, DNSSEC is enabled on a zone-by-zone
  basis. When a zone is DNSSEC-enabled, it is also known as "signed". Below are
  the areas that you should consider for possible hardware enhancements for an
  authoritative server with signed zones:

   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <simpara><emphasis>CPU</emphasis>: DNSSEC signed zone requires periodic
     re-signing, which is a cryptographic function that is CPU intensive. If
     your DNS zone is dynamic or changes frequently, it also adds to higher CPU
     loads.</simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <simpara><emphasis>System storage</emphasis>: A signed zone is definitely
     larger than an unsigned zone. How much larger? See <xref
     linkend="your-zone-before-and-after-dnssec" /> for a comparison
     example. Roughly speaking, you could expect your zone file to grow at
     least three times as large, usually more.</simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <simpara><emphasis>System memory</emphasis>: Larger DNS zone files take up
     not only more storage space on the file system, but also more space when
     they are loaded into system memory.</simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <simpara><emphasis>Network interfaces</emphasis>: While your authoritative
     name servers will begin sending back larger responses, it is unlikely that
     you need to upgrade your network interface card (NIC) on the name server,
     unless you have some truly out-dated hardware.</simpara>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist></para>

  <para>One of the factors to consider, but you really have no control over, is
  how many users who query your domain name have DNSSEC enabled. It is
  estimated in late 2014, that roughly 10% to 15% of the Internet DNS queries
  are DNSSEC aware. This translates to roughly 10% to 15% of the DNS queries
  for your domain will take advantage the additional security features, which
  result in the increased system load and possibly network traffic.</para>

 </section>
</section>
