<section id="what-does-dnssec-add-to-dns">
 <title>What does DNSSEC Add to DNS?</title>

 <!-- TODO: 
  Before talking about what is added to DNSSEC, do a very fast review of the
  use of public key cryptography for non-crypto geeks, and the use of digital
  signatures. Talk a little bit about key pairs, ZSK, and KSK, how keys are
  generated or obtained, but defer most of this to later sections. Talk at very
  high level of the "added" task of uploading DS records to parent, since this
  is a new concept for most zone administrators.
 -->

 <para>DNSSEC introduces six new resource record types:
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>RRSIG (digital signature)</simpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>DNSKEY (public key)</simpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>DS (parent-child)</simpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>NSEC (proof of nonexistence)</simpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>NSEC3 (proof of nonexistence)</simpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>NSEC3PARAM (proof of nonexistence)</simpara>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </para>

 <para>This guide will not dissect into the anatomy of each resource record
 type in detail, below is a short introduction on each of the new record types:

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <simpara><emphasis>RRSIG</emphasis>: With DNSSEC enabled, just about every
    DNS answer (A, PTR, MX, SOA, etc.) will come with at least one RRSIG, or
    resource record signature. These signatures are used by recursive name
    servers, also known as validating resolvers, to verify the answers
    received. To learn how digital signatures are generated and used, see <xref
    linkend="how-are-answers-verified" />.</simpara>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <simpara><emphasis>DNSKEY</emphasis>: DNSSEC relies on public key
    cryptography for data authenticity and integrity. There are several keys
    used in DNSSEC, some private, some public. The public keys are published to
    the world as part of the zone data, and they are stored in the DNSKEY
    record type. Please see <xref linkend="signing-generate-keys-explained" />
    to learn more.</simpara>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <simpara><emphasis>DS</emphasis>: One of the key components of DNSSEC is
    that the parent zone can "vouch" for its child zone. DS record is
    verifiable information a parent zone keeps on its child as part of the
    chain of trust. To learn more about Chain of Trust, see <xref
    linkend="chain-of-trust" />.</simpara>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist></para>

 <para>The NSEC, NSEC3, and NSEC3PARAM resource records all deal with a very
 interesting problem: proving that something really does not exist.  We will
 look at these record types in more detail in <xref
 linkend="advanced-discussions-proof-of-nonexistence" />.</para>

</section>

