<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY mdash  "&#x2014;" >
]>
<section id="signing-maintenance-tasks">
 <title>Maintenance Tasks</title>
 <para>Zone data is signed and the parent zone has published your DS records &mdash; at this
 point your zone is officially secure. When other validating resolvers lookup
 information in your zone, they are able to follow the 12-step process as
 described in <xref linkend="how-does-dnssec-change-dns-lookup-revisited" />
 and verify the authenticity and integrity of the answers.</para>

 <para>There is not that much left for you to do, as the DNS administrator, at
 an ongoing basis. Whenever you update your zone, BIND will automatically
 resign your zone with new RRSIG and NSEC or NSEC3 records, and even increment
 the serial number for you.  If you choose to split your keys into a KSK
 and ZSK, the rolling of the ZSK is completely automatic. Rolling of
 a KSK or CSK requires manual intervention.</para>

 <para>The only manual tasks for you to do are to monitor KSK or CSK key
 rolls and pass the new DS record to the parent zone - and you may not
 even have to do that if the parent can process CDS or CDNSKEY
 records.</para>

 <section id="cds-cdnskey">
  <title>The CDS and CDNSKEY Resource Records</title>
  <para>Passing the DS record to the organization running the parent
  zone has always been recognised as a bottleneck in the key rollover
  process.  To automate the process the CDS and CDNSKEY resource records were
  introduced.</para>

  <para>The CDS and CDNSKEY records are identical to the DS and DNSKEY
  records, except in the type code and the name.  When such a record appears
  in the child zone, it is a signal to the parent that it should update the
  DS it has for that zone.  In essence, what happens is that the parent
  polls the child zone and notices the presence of either or both of the CDS
  and CDNSKEY records.  It checks these records in the usual way i.e., that they
  are signed by a valid key for the zone. If the
  record(s) successfully validate a new DS record (copied from a CDS record
  or calculated from a CDNSKEY one) is added to the parent's DS RRset
  for the child.</para>
 </section>

 <section id="working-with-the-parent-2">
  <title>Working with the Parent Zone (2)</title>
  <para>If your parent zone does support polling for CDS/CDNSKEY records, you
  are almost there.  When BIND publishes these records, they will be uploaded
  and the DS record published in the parent.... we hope.
  At the time of writing (April 2020) BIND will not check for the
  presence of a DS record in the parent zone before completing the KSK or
  CSK rollover and withdrawing the old key.  Instead, it assumes that
  the operation will be completed within the time period set by the
  <code>parent-registration-delay</code> value in the DNSSEC policy
  <footnote><para>So if the parent zone supports CDS/CDNSKEY,
  why did we have to manually upload the DS record when we first signed the
  zone?  The answer is down to security.  Until our zone was signed, the parent
  couldn't be sure that a CDS or CDNSKEY record it obtained really did come from
  the zone. So some other form of secure had to be used to obtain the information.
  </para></footnote>.</para>

  <para>If your parent doesn't support CDS/CDNSKEY, when a new KSK appears in your
  zone, you will have to supply the DNSKEY or DS record to the zone manually,
  probably using the same mechanism you used to upload the records for the first
  time.</para>

  <para>Either way, you need to monitor the progress of a KSK or CSK roll.  Look
  for the introduction of the CDS and CDNSKEY records in the zone.  If required,
  send the DS record to the parent zone manually.  And monitor the parent zone to
  ensure that the DS record appears at the correct time.</para>

 </section>
</section>
