<section id="signing-easy-start-explained">
 <title>Signing Easy Start Explained</title> 

 <!-- === Enable Automatic Maintenance Explained === -->
 <section id="enable-automatic-maintenance-explained">
  <title>Enable Automatic DNSSEC Maintenance Explained</title>
  <para>Signing a zone requires a number of separate steps:</para>

   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>Generation of the keys to sign the zone.</simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>Inclusion of the keys into the zone.</simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>Signing of the records in the file (including the
     generation of the NSEC or NSEC3 records).</simpara>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

  <para>Maintaining it comprises a set of ongoing tasks:</para>

   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>Re-signing the zone as signatures approach expiration.</simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>Generation of new keys as the time approaches for a key roll.</simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>Inclusion of new keys into the zone when the rollover starts.</simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>Transition from signing the zone with the old set of keys to signing
     the zone with the new set of keys.</simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>Waiting the appropriate interval before removing the old keys
     from the zone.</simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>Deleting the old keys.</simpara>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

   <para>That is a lot of complexity, and it is all handled with the
   single <code>dnssec-policy default</code> statement. We will see
   later on (in section <xref linkend="signing-custom-policy"/>) how the
   these actions can be tuned by setting up our own DNSSEC policy with
   customized parameters. In many cases though, the defaults are
   adequate.  After reading the rest of this guide, you may decide that
   you do need to tweak the parameters or use an alternative signing
   method.  But if not, that's it - you can forget about DNSSEC, there
   is nothing more to do.</para>

   <para>At the time of writing (April 2020), <code>dnssec-policy</code> is
   still a relatively new feature in BIND.  As such, although it is the
   preferred way to run DNSSEC in your zone, it can't do everything
   that you can do with a more "hands on" approach to signing and key
   maintenance.  For this reason, we will be covering alternative signing
   techniques <xref linkend="signing-alternative-ways"/>.</para>
 </section>
</section>
